Guide to the Women's History Anthology Collection, 1826-1974 AIS.1974.21
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Women's History Anthology Collection
1826-1974
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Greenwald, Maurine Weiner
AIS.1974.21
1.44 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
This collection concerns the historical role of the woman in the United States from Colonial to present time. The materials include photocopied manuscripts and articles from books, pamphlets, periodicals, and newspapers, together with photocopied oral interview transcripts, fables, poems, and songs.
Scope and Content Notes
The Women's History Anthology Collection concerns the historical role of the woman in the United States from Colonial times(1826) to 1974. This collection was duplicated from the file brought together by several individuals who were preparing an anthology of readings on the historical role of women in the United States.
The collection consists largely of published materials relating to the labor issues and social conditions of women in the late 19th and early 20th century. The collection covers labor activism, ethnic groups, and women's liberation movements in areas around the United States. The published material includes articles from books, pamphlets, periodicals, and newspapers. Other materials include manuscripts, oral interview transcripts, fables, poems, and songs. Each genre of material relates to a series in the collection. The items are arranged alphabetically within the series by author, organization, or title of article.
An addition of subject files relating to pertinent women's issues was added to the collection in 1976. This addition is considered a separate series in the collection and is arranged alphabetically according to subject. The items cover a wide range of social issues and consist of published material from periodicals, books, and pamphlets from 1973-1974. A bibliography of books and phamphlets on Women in China and the Women's Liberation Movement is included.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Maureen Greenwald on June 24, 1974.
Existence and Location of Copies
This collection has been photocopied from the originals. The originals were returned to the donor.
Previous Citation
Women's History Anthology Collection, 1826-1974, AIS.1974.21, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Women's History Collectanea, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Ethnic groups; Social action; Women; Women -- Conduct of life; Women -- Interviews; Women -- United States -- History -- Sources; Women -- Social conditions; United States -- Social conditions; United States -- History -- Sources; Labor; Greenwald, Maurine Weiner
- Manuscripts, I.
  - Butler's Proclamation concerning Women of New Orleans, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clark, Sue Anislie; letter to Mrs. Raymond Robins, President National Women's Trade Union League, (Papers, National Archives, Library of Congress, Headquarters Records), June 1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Durha, Lydia, and Fisher, France; "Union Participation and Representation" Speech delivered at the National UPWA Conf. on Women (United Packinghouse Workers File, Wisconsin State Historical Society) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dwight Manufacturing Company, Chicopee, Mass. [Misc. papers] (From Collection at Baker Library, Harvard University) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Faler, Paul; The Cultural Side of the Revolution: Lynn, Mass. Shoemakers and Industrial Morality, (Papers, National Archives, Library of Congress, Headquarters Records), 1826-1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Flynn, Elizabeth G.; "What Price Housework?", (Ltr. to New Masses, March 4, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gubbay, Michele; The Two O'Clock Lounge, 24, no. 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Knights of Labor, Letter to membership in re Women's Work, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Letters from Charleston Hospital Strikers", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - M'Creery, Maude; "Women Folk -- The Shock Troops", Unpublished Ms in the Wisconsin State Historical Society (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Neuman, Pauline; Letter to Rose Schneidenman From the Schneiderman Papers, Taminent Library, NYU, July 11, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Powderly, Terrence; Letter to R. Glocking in re Sister Barry, (From Letterbook 48, C.U.T.V.P. Papers), April 10, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Stupek, Sophie; "Organizers' Reports" (Papers of American Federation of Hosiery Workers, Series 5, Wisconsin State Elist. Society (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Women in Utopian Societies (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Published Material, II.
  - Are Women Hard to Organize? in the Survey, p. 741-742, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Baer, Barbara L. and Matthews, Glenna, The Women of the Boycott in the Nation, February 23, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Baker, Illelen, Women in War Industries, Chapter IV, "Hours of Work" and Chapter V, "Wage Rates and Wage Policies" (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bakke, Wight, Selectins from Citizens Without Work, (New Haven, Yale) p. 132-139, 182-183, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bowen, Margaret, The Story of the Elizabethton Strike in American Federalist, p. 664-668, June, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bowen, Margaret, Working Conditions in the Textile Industry from U.S. Senate Committee on Manufactures. Hearings on S. Res. 49. Quoted in American Labor. Working Conditions of the Textile Industry in North Carolina, South Carolina, and Tennessee. 71st Congress, 1st Session, p. 78-86, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Brooklyn Mob Loots Butcher Shops in NYT, p. 2, May 26, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bruere, Martha Bensley, The Triangle Fire in Life and Labor, p. 137-141, May, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Clark, Jessie, Colored Women in the Industries of New York City, p. 39, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Clark, Mrs. Laura (Downs), The Original Diary of Mrs. Laura (Downs) Clark, of Wakeman, Ohio in Firelands Pioneer, Series XXI, p. 2308-2326, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Clark, Sue Ainslie, Women Laundry Workers in New York in McClures, p. 401-414, February, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Colton, Jennifer, Why I Quit Working in Good Housekeeping, September, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Congress of Ind. Organization, Resolution #8 in re Women's Auxiliaries, November 14-18, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cowley, Joyce, 9 Working Mothers and Delinquency in The Militant, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cramer, Jane Smith, Should Women Support the Equal Rights Amendment? in Independent Woman, p. 148-149, 171-174, May, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Davies, Margery, Woman's Place is at the Typewriter; the Feminization of Clerical Labor Force, in Ms, January 1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Davis, Angela, Reflections on the Black Women's Role in the Community of Slaves in Black Scholar, p. 3-17, December, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - The Day's Work in a Cannery in Life and Labor, p. 326-328, November, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Denied My Sex in True Romance, April, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Donovan, Frances, Selections from The Woman Who Waits (Boston, Gorham, Pa.), 1921 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Dutcher, Elisabeth, Budgets of the Triangle Fire Victims in Life and Labor, p. 265-267, September, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Employment of Women in Independent, 1912, p.2691-3 and 1901, p.834-7 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Enid Dubois from studs Terkel, Works, Pantheon, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Flynn, Elisabeth G., The Case of Margaret Sanger in Solidarity, July 31, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Flynn, Elisabeth G., The I.W.W. Call to Women in Solidarity, July 31, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Flynn, Elisabeth G., One Boss Less--The Minersville Strike in International Socialist Review, July, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Flynn, Elisabeth G., Problems Organizing Women in Solidarity, July 15, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Flynn, Elisabeth G., Talk of Child Care? But We Need Action in The Worker, January 17, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Flynn, Elisabeth G., The Truth about the Paterson Strike, talk delivered at the New York Civic Club Forum, January 31, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Flynn, Elisabeth G., A Woman Who Died for Labor in August 1919 in The Daily Worker, August, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Flynn, Elisabeth G., Women in Industry Should Organize in Industrial Worker, Transcript from holdings of the Tamiment Library, New York., June 1, 1911. (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Frontier Mother, excerpts (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Giffen, Jerena East, Add a Pinch and Lump: Missouri Women in the 1820's in Missouri Historical Review, p. 478-504, July, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Girls' Own Stories in Life and Labor, p. 51-52, February, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - The Great Showmakers' Strike from Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, p. 1-2, March 17, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Harland, Marion, One Housewife's Protest in Independent, p. 564-5, March, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Hasanovitz, Elizabeth, Selections from One of Them (Boston, Houghton, Mifflin, 1918), p. 212-215 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Haynes, Elizabeth Ross, Two Million Negro Women at Work in Southern Workman, p. 64-72, February, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Herbst, Alma, Selections from Negro in the Slaughtering and Meat Packing Industry in Chicago (Boston, Houghton, Mifflin, 1932) (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Hom, Shirley, Working in a Cannery in Asian Women (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - In Harlan County Women Take Up the Fight (source unknown), January 14, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Johnson, Edrena, Black Diary: A Week in the Charleston Jailhouse in Manhattan Tribune, July 5, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Johnson, Olive M., Woman and the Socialist Movement from New York Labor News Co., n.d., 48p. (Box 1, Folder 56A)
  - Kahn, Kathy, A sweatshop don't ever pay enough from Mountain Life and Work, p. 18-21, April, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Knights of Labor, General Assembly Proceedings, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Knights of Labor, Report from the General Instuctor and Director of Woman's Work, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Labor in New York: Its Circumstances, Conditions and Rewards in New York Tribune, August 14, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Lang, Lucy Robins, Selections from Tomorrow is Beautiful (N.Y., Macmillan, 1948), p. 14-26 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Lauber, Almon Wheeler, Indian Slavery in Colonial Times, N.Y., p. 214-297, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - LeSueur, Meridel, They Follow Us Girls,p.109-113 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Lewis, Oscar, Effects of the fur trade upon the Blackfoot, Chapter VI in The Effects of White contact upon Blackfoot Culture with special reference to the role of the fur trade, p. 34-50 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Life and Labor, Letter by a New Yorker to Life and Labor, p.384, December, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Lobenz, Johanna, Selections from The Older Woman in Industry,(CN.Y., 1929) p.109-113 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Lutz, Alma, Shall Women's Work be Regulated by Law? in Atlantic Monthly, p. 321-327, September, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Lutz, Alma, Why Discharge Women First? in Independent Woman, p. 535-537, December, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - McKee, Samuel, Apprenticeship from Labor in Colonial New York, 1664-1776, p. 70, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - McKee, Samuel, Indentured Servitude from Labor in Colonial New York, 1664-1776, p. 103-111, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Maley, Anna A., The Stuff of which Revolutionists are Made in The Progressive Women, p. 10, May, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Mills, C. Wright, et. al., The Puerto Rican Journey, (N.Y., Harper Brother, 1950) (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Nester, Agnes, A Factory Made by a Strike in The Life and Labor, p. 23-24, January, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Occupations from Ogibwa Woman (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - O'Connell, John and O'Brien, John. Dialogue reflecting "the underlying reluctant and patronizing attitude of men toward women who were carrying their load and carrying it well". Quoted from Richard Finnie in Marinship: the history of a Wartime Shipyard, (San Francisco, 1947) (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - O'Connor, Julia S., History of the Organized Telephone Operators' Movement in The Union Telephone Operator, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Ogden, Jean, Organizing the Food Workers in Labor Age, p. 13, April, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Oil, Chemical and Atomic Workers Int. Union. Excerpts from miscellaneous publications. (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - O'Reilly, Leonora, The Story of Kalamazoo in Life and Labor, p. 228-230, August, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Our Working Classes in New York Times, Wednesday, March 17, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Packard, Esther, Selections from A Study of Living Conditions of Self-Supporting Women in New York City, N.Y., Metropolitan Bd. of the YMCA, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Parry, Shirley, Union Organizer in Women, A Journal of Liberation, volume 2 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Pilgrims Progress in a Telephone Exchange in Life and Labor, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Razowsky, Cecilia, What Every Emigrant Should Know, N.Y. Council of Jewish Women, p. 8-49, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Rose, Madeline Belkin, Selections from a transcript of an oral interview with Lillian Belkin (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Rosinos, Jean R., Marching Women of Illinois in Labor Age, p. 6-7. See women's auxiliaries, November, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Rozner, Sarah, Looking for a Job from an oral interview of Sarah Rozner by Sherna Gluck (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - A Servant Girl's Letter in Independent p. 37, January, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Shallcross, Ruth, Should Married Women Work? for the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, N.Y., Public Affairs Committee, p. 1-9,16-17, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Shields, Emma L., Negro Women and the Tobacco Industry in Life and Labor, p. 142-4, May, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Similarities of Oneida Women as workers with their Sisters in the 'outside world', source unknown, ca. 1855-1874 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Smith, Helen, Colonial days and ways gathered from Family Papers, N.Y., p. 111-119, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Tilmon, Johnnie, Welfare is a Women's Issue in Liberation News Service, #415, p. 15-16, February 26, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - To End Discriminations Against Women in Independent Woman, May, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Twining, Luella, The Philadelphia Situation in Progressive Women, volume 3, p. 4-5, May, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Two Little Heroines in Progressive Women, (volume and year unknown) (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - United Electrical Radio and Machine Workers of America, UE Fights for Women Workers, N.Y., p. 39, ca. 1952 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - U.S. Congress, Senate, Labor-Management Relations in Textile Industry. Hearings before the Subcommittee on Labor Management Relations of the Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare, 81st Congress, August 21-24, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - U.S. War Manpower Commission, America at War needs Women at Work, Washington, D.C., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - The United States Practical Receipt Book; or, Complete Book of Reference...by a practical Chemist, Philidelphia, extracts, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Vorse, Mary H., Selections from Labor's New Millions, p. 74-81,84-87,234-236, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Wage Earners' Suffrage League, Senators vs. Working Women, various paging (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Warner, Lucy A., Why Do People Look Down on Working Girls? in Far and Near, March, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Wolfson, Theresa, The Women's Auxiliary to the Trade Unions and Workers' Education (Workers Educational Pamphlet Series), N.Y., p. 6-19, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Women as Production Workers in War Plants in Smith College Studies in History (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - The Women at the Convention in The New Order, p.35, See: Women's Auxiliaries, May-June, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Women on the Night Shift in Life and Labor, p. 377-9, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Women's Auxiliaries, 1932-1938 (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Women's Auxiliaries: Congress of Ind. Organization Proc., Resolution #8 in Women's Auxiliaries, November 14-18, 1938; 1.
    - Women's Auxiliaries: Rosinos, Jean R., Marching Women of Illinois in The Labor Age, p.6-7, November, 1932; 2.
    - Women's Auxiliaries: The Women at the Convention in The New Order, p.35, May-June, 1938; 3.
  - Articles on how to start and run a Women's Auxiliary, Brooklyn (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Wood-Simons, May, Miner's Wives in Kansas in Life and Labor, p. 146-9, May, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - A Word to Workingmen in Journal of United Labor, Vol. VII, no.21, February 5, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - The Working Women in Workingman's Advocate, Vol. V, no.41, May 8, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Wright, Florence S., The Visiting Nurse in Industrial Welfare Work in Proc. of the National Safety Council, p. 546-553, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 113)
- Interviews, III.
  - Balkin, Lillian, Interview by Madeline Balkin Rose, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Miller, Edna, Oral history paper prepared by a student with Linda Gordon, University of Massachusetts, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Roberts, Lillian, Transcribed interview with Lillian Roberts, District Council 37, AFSCME, New York City, August 29, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Stein, Anne, Transcribed interview with Anne Stein, New York City, September 6, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 117)
- Fables, IV.
  - Hall, Bolton, Fables (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - A New Touch on the Times by a Daughter of Liberty, Broadside, 1779 (Box 2, Folder 118A)
- Poems, V.
  - Poems, sources from which reproduced unknown (Box 2, Folder 119)
- Songs, VI.
  - Songs, sources from which reproduced unknown (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - The Women's Auxiliary Theme Song, in 6-12 Labor Wi-Workers, The Peoples' Song Collection (Box 2, Folder 121)
- Subject Files, VII.
  - Arts (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - Birth Control (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Careers and career planning (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - Child Care (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - Education (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Feminist Movement (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - Health (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - Labor Unions (Box 3, Folder 129)
  - Lesbianism (Box 3, Folder 130)
  - Sex Discrimination (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - Socialism/Feminism (Box 3, Folder 132)
  - Women in China (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - Women's Liberation and Revolution (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - Women Workers (Box 3, Folder 135)